have you ever wanted to trisect an angle
stick around and I'll show you one
technique to do this
the problem of trisecting an angle
requires us to take a given angle Alpha
and using classical tools find two lines
that trisect the angle into three pieces
all with an angle measure of alpha over
three it turns out that you cannot
trisect a general angle using a straight
edge Encompass but it might be possible
if we add an extra tool
polar curve R equals Theta is called the
Archimedes spiral let's take a look at
the graph of this spiral right here
you cannot construct the Archimedes
spiral using Straight Edge Encompass
however if we add the spiral as one of
our tools we may be able to use this
tool along with the straight edge
Encompass to trisect the angle we won't
actually need the entire Archimedes
spiral to do this just the bit that lies
between 0 and 2 pi
let's imagine that we have the unit
circle drawn like this
and that we have two points one along
the x-axis and the other one creating a
line with an angle of alpha the arc on
the unit circle subtending the angle
Alpha has an arc length of length Alpha
now let's draw the Archimedes spiral R
equals Theta this intersects our Top
Line at a point let's call the point P
because P lies on the line created by
angle Alpha it has an angle of Alpha and
because it lies on the Archimedes spiral
it must create a radius of length Alpha
from the origin we can then use our
straight edge Encompass to divide the
line from the origin to the point P into
three equal pieces like this we use our
Compass to create this Arc of radius
Alpha over 3. it intersects the
archimedian spiral at a point q and
because Q has a radius of alpha over 3
its angle must be Alpha over 3.
similarly we construct this Arc of
radius 2 Alpha over 3 which intersects
the Archimedean spiral at a point R
because R has a radius of 2 Alpha over
three its angle is 2 Alpha over three as
well
and now we can finish off our problem we
connect the origin to point q and the
origin to point R
and sure enough we have divided the
angle Alpha into three separate angles
all of measure Alpha over three
this means that we've used the
Archimedes spiral to trisect any angle
Alpha